Guide to Michael Neyman's Screen adaptation, stills, and film for the original version of John Steinbeck's story FLIGHT, 1957-1961
Department of Special Collections
Neyman, Michael. Screen adaptation, stills, and film for the original version of John Steinbeck's story FLIGHT,
1957-1961
M0767
Neyman, Michael
3.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1995.
Biography
Neyman had read FLIGHT in Berkeley High School; he wrote a screenplay in 1955; succeeded in obtaining the rights to film it in 1956 "through the kindness of John Steinbeck," and by 1959 succeeded in obtaining $80,000 from 27 shareholders in a corporation. He was then 23. But he went over budget and the picture was taken away from him by the principal investor, Barnaby Conrad, and both script and footage changed considerably. Michael Neyman studied cinema at USC, continued his career as a professional cameraman, but never again tackled a theatrical feature. A 1959 column by Paine Knickerbocker quotes Steinbeck at the time on Neyman: "Your script of 'FLIGHT' is the most exact translation of story to film I have ever seen. There is no softening, no sweetening, no attempt to sentimentalize. But I have not the slightest idea wehter it will work." In 1955 Steinbeck gave Neyman a two-year option, with the proviso he would approve the finished work. In 1959 Steinbeck extended the option and withdrew the demand. By the time Neyman was out of the picture and the investors had ponied up $240,000, Steinbeck spent a weekend writing and recording a commentary to soup up the picture, for producer Conrad.
Scope and Content
Included are Neyman's original versions: some preliminary film shots, his film, such of it as has been preserved, stills from the film and related prints, correspondence, publicity from his day, and ephemera.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Conrad, Barnaby, 1922-; Drutman, Irving.; Grunwald, Henry.; Hitchcock, Alfred, 1899-; Knickerbocker, Paine.; McClure, Michael.; McCord, Ted, d. 1976.; Otis, Elizabeth.; Parkinson, Thomas.; Scanlon, Bob.; Scott, Henry.; Steinbeck, John, 1902-1968.; Wilisie, Mike.; Zinneman, Fred, 1907-; Motion pictures.; Negatives.; Photoprints.; Scripts.
Collection Contents
- "Flight" script. Video/audio version. [June 1957] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Flight" script. Stencils. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Flight" shooting script revised. Video/audio version. [Oct.1958] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Flight" outline. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Barnaby Conrad's suggestions for revising the script. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Flight" stencil for film teaser opener. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Flight" Production, Inc. stationery. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Flight" Film Register (for Box #2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Prints (Reuben Segura). (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Flight" Publicity Photos. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Flight" Film Stills. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Flight" Film Stills. [Dec. 1960] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Flight", 62 prints of film scenes. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Flight", 28 prints of film scenes. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Flight", various stills and prints. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Flight", prints [Miscellaneous]. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Flight", Photo Negatives. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Flight", captions for stills. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "Flight", bills and receipts. [1959-61] (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Newspaper clippings relating to the production of "Flight". [1957-59?] (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Correspondence to Michael Neyman. [Elizabeth Otis, Fred Zinneman, et. al.] [1960-66] (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence from Michael Neyman. [to John Steinbeck, Fred Zinneman, Alfred Hitchcock, Thomas Parkinson, Barnaby Conrad et. al.] [1960-1967] (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Material written by Michael Neyman: "Introduction"(autobiographical), "Previous Photographic Experience", Berkeley High School grade sheet (1951), "Preliminary Proposal", "Double Boomerang" (screenplay). (Box 1, Folder 23)
- #35. Core. Slate: Flight / Dir. Neyman / 11-2-59, Black and white, 35 mm. 380 feet. (Carton 2, Folder 1)
- #42. Duplicate., 35 mm. 250 feet. (Carton 2, Folder 2)
- #7. Slate: Flight / Neyman/ 10-16., 3'' core. Black and white, 35 mm. 260 feet. (Carton 2, Folder 3)
- #47. Slate: "Prod. Flight Revue / Dir. Neyman / 11-2-57., brown metal 400' reel. Black and white, 16 mm. Double perfs. (Carton 2, Folder 4)
- #34. Paper label: "Cam. orig. (rev.) w/mag TRK FLIGHT PILOT 1968 most valued film check splices". 1968, Brown 400' steel reel. Black and white, 16 mm. Single perfs. Three minutes. (Carton 2, Folder 5)
- #3. Original. Slate: "Flight / Dir. and Cam. Neyman / 10-28-59". (Carton 2, Folder 6)
- #48 Slate: "Prod. E Ramirez-test / Dir. and Cam. Neyman / Produced by Ruth Dwyer Agency.9-3-56., Tails out on 2'' core. Black and white, 16 mm. Double perfs. (Carton 2, Folder 7)
- #38. Core. Black and white 35 mm. Slate: "Flight / Neyman / 7-2-59., 250 feet. (Carton 2, Folder 8)
- #4 Flipped, reversed, etc., Black and white, 35 mm. 200 feet. (Carton 2, Folder 9)
- Bundle of film strip negatives for "Light Test". (Carton 2, Folder 10)
- Bundle of film strip negatives for "Light Test". (Carton 2, Folder 11)
- Bundle of film strip negatives for "Light Test". (Carton 2, Folder 12)
- Bundle of film strip negatives for "Light Test". (Carton 2, Folder 13)
- "Flight". Oversized photographs and contact prints. (Box 3, Folder 1)